to organization
and today should be
a good one because we are here with
eugene who's going to be talking to us
about decentralization and smart
contracts and all kinds of other things
we also have this
interactive whiteboard
slide deck here so please write any
comments
in the chat
and uh
as soon as eugene is back
i'm sure he'll begin his initial
presentation but welcome everybody
looking forward to seeing your comments
in the chat
and
welcome back
your re-entry
please
provide a introduction and some context
and really looking forward to this of
course i got so excited to begin with
that i closed out the wrong tab so it's
always a good beginning but thank you
for for hosting me daniel excited to be
here with the actonflab uh and to get to
talk a little bit about the
centralization
and yeah kind of see where the
conversation goes so definitely really
excited to hear what folks are thinking
about and so please at any point if this
isn't going kind of deep enough uh on
any specific term you want more clarity
on anything please please feel free to
uh mention it in the chat we will
definitely be happy to to bring it up in
conversation
so just to begin i'm eugene leventhal
i'm currently the head of operations at
the smart contract research forum we're
a grant funded organization in the smart
contract space or in the web 3 space
overall excuse me
and our focus is very much on helping to
advance research around web 3. the
starting point for that is just
connecting folks from industry and
academia
and we're exploring a lot of various
questions about what is public good
infrastructure for research in web 3 but
also for science more broadly look like
so uh very very happy to talk about
smart contract research forum or scarf
as we colloquially call it uh ad nauseam
but yeah for for today the focus is on
decentralization itself so i want to
take it there
but
the thing i wanted to kind of start off
with and and uh mention as the
genesis of this conversation is the fact
that the space of web 3 even the term
web 3 right it's one i i came across
this uh github repo of just all these
articles that where it's very well known
technologists uh explaining why web 3 is
all a bunch of baloney and none of this
makes sense and uh in all fairness there
is a lot of enthusiasm in this space
that leads to there probably being more
focus on areas that um you know uh might
have
rockier grounds than others but the goal
of this session is really to delve into
a term that if you've been part of
anything blockchain crypto web 3 in any
kind of way you've definitely heard the
term decentralization thrown around
because the whole
dichotomy and i don't know if it's even
fair to call it a dichotomy because that
oversimplifies the idea but at least
this idea of a spectrum between they're
centralized and somewhere along the line
there's decentralized um what does that
actually mean to be decentralized
and for me another thing which i always
love thinking not in binaries but sort
of in spectra is decentralization an
endpoint or is it itself only a a
certain check mark on a much wider
spectra
where maybe centralization to full
peer-to-peer distribution is the actual
ends of it where everything goes through
one party or goes through everyone in
the system and there's sort of a you
know gradients in between but i think
right we can delve right into more of
the technical definition of the
architecture the history of the term of
decentralization or something like that
but to zoom out i kind of like thinking
about decentralization from at least two
high-level buckets one is who are we
talking about and the other is what are
we talking about the who pertains to are
we talking about owners of a system or
users of a system and that was users of
the system so
those vary greatly right because if
we're talking about ownership that's
where things like co-ops the whole
cooperative ownership movement i mean
that has had millennia behind it right
that's where that pertains but there's
also a there could be a scenario where
users use a system that on an
architectural perspective is
decentralized in terms of there not
being a single point of centralization i
know i still haven't defined it yet
that's intentional um but
the for the user right they could have
no ownership in the state so it's not as
though we mean decentralized
decentralization itself does not mean
cooperatively owned per se right so
let's suss apart who is actually using
it and who is owning the thing that
we're talking about
and then when it comes to actually
thinking about the what gets
decentralized right i think that's where
it's important to think on the one hand
there's the infrastructure layer and
more the application layer
and alongside that it's sort of what is
the actual domain of whatever we're
talking about right because
infrastructure or application is more of
uh
the the the uh the dimension of kind of
uh architecture so to say and the actual
domain can be in terms of knowledge
right our databases are they uh with
known knowledge is that easily
accessible right you one can argue that
uh libraries right the whole goal of or
ego of libraries was to make information
more accessible it's taking it away from
a single place and opening it up to have
more
people being able to interact with it
and that can relate to knowledge to
decision making or communications to
actual resources
and so right i'm kind of dancing around
a few of these concepts around
decentralization but again what am i
actually talking about right so for me
it always comes down to if we're talking
about decentralization it needs to be in
the context of a system right
decentralization is not just something
that appears or disappears right it's
only in the context of systems and when
we think of those systems again are we
we can be thinking about
and let's just think of this from from
say the what perspective right
infrastructure apps what are the actual
domain of those infrastructure apps when
we talk about those things
centralization or decentralization can
relate to power dynamics or who actually
gets to make the decision of how all of
these things are run at the end of the
day i know in the web 3 space there's
been a lot of
exit to dow you know just exiting uh to
community is a more broad term that i i
believe came from nathan schneider and
some other folks working on now the
project exit to community but the whole
idea of how can we actually let some of
the decision making
uh and uh knowledge creation in our
community be both owned by and used by
the same set of folks and and kind of
keep expanding that set and i think
that's a lovely concept but a lot of the
time decentralization at least from some
of the conversations around web3 that i
hear they start conflating a lot of
things and which is why i like breaking
it down to are we actually talking about
the owners and users and are we talking
to the infrastructure app player or and
what is the actual domain of those
things and once you map that out then
you can start being a little more
nuanced in trying to
break out what exactly it is we want to
explore the idea of decentralizing
because the decentralization and power
go hand in hand but again you need to be
more specific in your terms and thinking
about which part of a system
you actually want to expand that scope
of power around otherwise it can be very
tough to build the necessary
requirements of culture and community
around this because again if you are
trying to truly decentralize something
that means you're going off to let more
people have power in the system and
more people it just equals more
messiness right and that's not a
judgment call i i think that that can at
least for anyone who's genuinely you
know try to make a decision with one
other people or with a hundred other
people and let me know the scenario
where it's easier with the hundred than
with the one uh and i'm sure you can
always find an exception right but as a
rule of thumb uh that does seem to hold
and so
that's kind of one thing i wanted to to
start with in terms of decentralization
overall and this kind of diffusion of
power and again being particular with
the terms of where in the system are we
thinking of power and for whom does that
power apply or apply to um
and now that we've
gotten at least some kind of a baseline
of decentralization now let's jump into
what do i actually mean when i say
something like decentralizing science
because if you've been following some uh
you know random or not random but then
following certain niches of crypto
twitter which i recognize crypto
twitters already in niche so niche among
niches but you know you might have seen
the terms decide coming up i think in
september october was the first time i i
believe i could find some kind of record
of it on twitter but um right this is a
relatively new term dsi decentralizing
science or decentralized science so
we're diffusing the power around the
creation or the propagation right around
what of science science is itself a very
uh high level term that can mean a lot
of different things to a lot of people
so
i like to think of right if we're
breaking it down into the highest level
but separate parts there's the actual
research side so there's someone who has
an existing base of knowledge who has a
theory about something that is not
captured in that base of knowledge and
wants to run some kind of tests to
appear to somehow amend or append the
existing base of knowledge with new
information so that's what i see as the
actual research function then there's
the review function
some people looked into a thing and want
to claim that it is true or not how do
we double check that right so the the
quality assurance layer over research
and then there's the publication of
research which should not be conflated
with media or publications overall
because research publication as as it
stands today and i can't speak this
confidently globally but at least in the
states research publication and usable
kind of interactable publication are two
very different things sort of you know
the springers the acms the ieees their
goal is not to get 10 million hits in
academic paper you know they're working
within a very specific system of
producing academic research that is
connected to the rev to the existing
structures of research and review when
it comes to just pure media there it
becomes a lot of the time how do you get
it to as many people as possible which
means how do you sometimes lose the
depth of the point to make it easier to
digest in a short amount of time which
is it inherently contradictory to
research which is let's go as deep as
possible on as narrow a set of things as
we can to actually learn something or
add to some kind of base of knowledge
around that more narrow deep set of
things so in my sort of pipeline of
high level pipeline of science it's
there's research which gets reviewed and
then it gets published
but
that inherently does not capture
everything out of uh coming out of
academia or inherently coming out of
any brilliant minds around the planet
who have good ideas that you know should
be explored and there's the question of
who has access to be doing research in
the first place right in the states
today if you're not at a top 10 top 50
at least research institution you're not
in a top corporation that actually has
an r d department that's meaningfully
funded which is not the case at all
corporations
and you're not at a government agency
dedicated to research you're probably
gonna have a hard time having a seat at
the table unless you find a way to break
into one of those areas right so we can
start thinking of well do we mean
decentralizing research means everyone
should get to do research maybe i'm not
here to sort of give a yay or an a but
it's starting to think of well what do
we mean about the power there is it who
actually gets access to be a researcher
is it who gets to have a call and be
part of the decision of what gets funded
is it something about the actual
interaction with the research
information right those are all
different aspects of what could we be
talking about when we're talking about
ad or changing around the power dynamics
around research itself
but again that's just the first step
because then we just got to jump to
review even if we've ironed all that out
we have a clear sense of what it means
to decentralize research well who is
actually going to be responsible for
quality assurance and i think that
you know there's no shortage of
information on some of the current
challenges in peer review
i don't want to distract myself now but
i can pull together a link later when i
have a moment a professor from carnegie
mellon nihar shah
he and another professor from cmu zach
lipton did a great joint presentation
that i i know that their slides are
publicly available that i'll have linked
to they did a great outline of all of
the known research studies delving into
the current problems with uh peer review
and i i don't want to be misquoting but
i think it's somewhere in the 70 to 100
range of academic studies just exploring
very particular problems in peer review
right so this is not as though i'm
someone from outside academia raising a
red flag that doesn't exist right talk
to a tenured faculty member and they
will probably be the first one to tell
you all the problems with the peer
review structure of today um so one of
the challenges is if you ask the people
who are doing the research to be their
own reviewers
right there's a clear conflict of
interest there if you tell me to produce
something and review it
there's reason to believe that i will
have the incentive to
be light on the review and just push
whatever i want to produce so the
separation of those two functions is
very important but the question of you
know should reviewers be anonymous or
not should reviewers be compensated or
not
again should everyone be able to be a
reviewer should everyone have a seat at
the table of being to review or do you
need a bare minimum set of
qualifications to even you know be
allowed to be a reviewer in whatever a
future system of review might be
and then finally there's the aspect of
the actual publication
of
you've done the research you've gotten
it reviewed now it has to go somewhere
and at least the current norm a lot of
the time in the top research institution
is via a journal or conference or some
kind of very high level or very uh
esteemed publication right you might
have heard the the motto so to say
publish or perish which i think is a
good encapsulation of the incentive
problems around academia for research
faculty where a lot of the time you know
if you're in the
top kind of one percent of institutions
you might be focused on more headline
catching uh research because you might
actually be the pipeline where you have
the relationships with the largest media
organizations and they come to you for
some kind of fancy you know new breaking
research on people and the brain and
this is what this means for how all of
us
you know the kind of stuff mainstream
media likes to oversimplify when it
comes to uh talking about research
publicly
uh on the other side of it
there's also uh or sort of excuse me
with the aspect of publisher parish
that's just in the top one percent if
you go into more of the uh the kind of
the global majority of research
institutions the game that's being
played is different where it's a volume
play where your ability to progress as a
tenured faculty member has pressures on
it to see how many things you've
actually published that hit some kind of
reputable journal
and right those are all incentives that
make it tough for people to just focus
on the purity of the act of review and
there's a whole separate question right
does the purity of the act matter as
long as we can figure figure out a
system and function so that we minimize
the amount of questionable science that
gets put out right what is the the bad
side of review
that uh research happens that comes to
faulty conclusions no one captures it
and someone tries building on it right
and that could actually lead to some
kind of problems if we think of the hard
sciences you know imagine a medical
device going out uh built on a
fundamental research premise that is
false right like people's lives could
actually be at risk in those kind of
scenarios so this isn't just some like
people playing with d5 money online
kinds of questions right this is science
more broadly so but again that whole
cycle of
research
review and publish still doesn't
actually get to how do we get this
research out of the ivory walls of
universities into the hands of people
who need to build it how do we actually
make this relevant to your average
person anywhere on the planet who might
wonder
what is the cutting edge of uh i don't
know quantum computing have to do with
me if i don't even know how to type a
line of code or explain how an email
gets from my phone to my computer or to
anything else nor do i care right i'm
busy with my own life and i have my own
priorities and problems why should i
care about any of this in the first
place right so there's already there's
the full research apparatus that we
talked about and a lot of the
institutions that do science reporting
or any kind of well let's actually get
this contextualized and larger
narratives
right what are the actual incentives
aligning them with
the researchers are them with the public
so there's a number of things in all of
these right all of these separate nodes
of the large system that is science that
themselves have a multitude of different
areas where we can explore what
decentralization might mean and how that
might impact the people in the system uh
or how that might impact people who
don't care about the system at all but
just want to have uh you know less
suffering more prosperity in their life
and how does it actually go from
theoretical science to genuinely
improving people's lives and the last
bit i'll kind of touch on before before
bringing this to be the actual
conversation it's intended to be um is
more on the behavioral side because
i know when i first got interested in
blockchain endows in the 2016 timeline
it felt very much that
there was just so much excitement that
oh we could be at the precipice of
making the thing that solves all of
humanity's problems right and if you've
studied the history of technology or of
any kind of advances that's a sentiment
that is not new a lot of people had a
lot of cutting edge advances at their
point in time thought that oh this could
be the thing that actually you know ends
uh world hunger or poverty or whatever
right that it could actually have these
mass global scale positive effects
but especially when it comes to
something like decentralization
i feel as though one of the questions
that i'm hoping we'll get into this
through conversation right but a
decentralized world right if we have
this kind of world where power gets
distributed from a very limited set of
players to a much wider base of
individuals
there's just more uncertainty there
right because
like it or not right and again look at
political governance in the full history
there
democracies are messier in the sense of
decision making because more people have
to come together but there's a lot of
benefits of that messiness i am
personally a huge fan of that messiness
because i think us working through
messiness is that it's it's the most
human thing we can be doing right we are
a social species and us working through
the messiness of coordination is part of
the exciting thing is that we get to
build higher order ideas uh as a species
like these laptops we're talking on or
any of the other great advances that we
now have
um and so i think
at the core of of
decentralization for me is an increase
in uncertainty and i think that that is
something that we don't like talking
about a lot in the space or at least i
have not heard many open discussions
about it because it runs counter to
human nature and desire right and like
let's look at that at a few different
dimensions right let's just think of us
as a pure biological creature let's take
away all of our socio social constructs
all of our socio-cultural constructs we
are just a biological mass right
i am personally
of the camp i am not a neuroscientist
but in my limited knowledge and
following some neuroscientists uh i i am
fully in the camp um of the lisa feldman
barrett's and the many others who are
now part of this growing school yeah our
brains are prediction machines that's
literally what they evolve to do is to
be much better at predicting what's
about to happen and so right what does
prediction mean it means that we we like
to model things out right and there's a
lex friedman has a great series of
interviews with lisa feldman barrett and
yoshobak and a few others that i'd be
happy to link to that i just love those
three to four hour discussions jumping
around neuroscience and consciousness
and everything else that you know that
makes sense to me that there's these
sort of there's cortical columns that
are focused on certain activities uh
there are sort of columns of neurons
being bunched together or really of
neural nets being bunched together to
sort of execute certain functions as you
kind of get more and more of these
together you need consolidation
functions right and we have models at
all different kinds of levels ranging
from uh very narrowly focused ones to
like hey what do i want to do with my
life tomorrow or a year from now right
like those are very complicated modeling
exercises but our brains are constantly
trying to model and modeling means
you're trying to map on you're trying to
limit uncertainty and create an actual
projection into the future of what might
happen and
why does centralization show up in a lot
of socio-cultural environments because
there's efficiency decentralization
right if one person gets to make all the
calls assuming they are good at making
calls and they're a good person with or
that they're shooting towards a
beneficial end right we will all be able
to move more quickly with that one as
opposed to 10 000 trying to make that
decision so
a lot of this natural evolution has
pushed us to want to minimize
uncertainty and yet we are inherently
trying to introduce a cultural element
that actually increases uncertainty
which for me again is very just counter
our biology and i think that right we
don't just have to think on that level
of our brain as prediction machines and
along those lines right how many
how easy is it right at the start of my
day and i'll just use the personal
example as an abstraction right at the
start of my day especially as someone
with chronic sleep issues and whatever i
start every day at the center of my
universe right and i have to be
intentional about reminding myself that
that voice inside my head that's yapping
as soon as my eyes open up that is not
the entirety of me that's actually one
of the nodes that constitute the entire
being and system that is eugene but at
the end of the day that's the thing that
i hear first and foremost and it's very
easy for me to just get caught up in the
emotionality of whatever that voice is
yammering on about
and to pretend that i need to be going
with it wherever it's taking me where i
have the ability through meditation
mindfulness through all different kinds
of practices to be like time out let's
go ahead and quiet that voice and let's
listen to other modes let's listen to
other nodes in the system of eugene and
right for me decentralization is a
psychological concept too if we think of
ourselves as a system do i just give
credence to the centralized view of the
voice of consciousness or do i actually
try to have a more decentralized view of
my being where i'm listening to every
single node that is part of my
constitution right before i started
meditating i never actually thought
about how does my back feel against the
chair that i'm sitting in as i'm right
like these little elements of focusing
attention and being intentional i think
those two words of intention and
attention are so important for where
behavioral level change begins and what
i don't see enough of in this space or
in a lot of spaces is the bridge between
behavioral level change and high level
philosophy so that's really why i wanted
to have this discussion today is because
i i'm happy to espouse tom blue in the
face of my my views on
why certain decentralization is great
and good for humanity and all this other
stuff but at the end of the day you can
have the best philosophical theory in
the history of humanity and if you don't
actually know how to get a single person
to start taking a step towards it is it
really useful so
for me i love jumping between the two
between what can i do to be a better
collective citizen of the groups and
systems that i'm in and jump to what
does that mean to inform my philosophy
of life and what is the link between
those two and how do i get a feedback
loop going and not just punting off to
philosophizing and abstracting which is
much easier than the the lower level of
understanding myself emotions and all of
the internal world side so that's kind
of that might have gone on a little
longer than i intended but that's my
where i'd like to kind of kick us off
okay
great
thank you for the introduction
and opening
set of ideas a lot of places to
jump in there
did you ever get to what
decentralization is
let's return to maybe that and then yeah
sure so yeah it's been a few other
places
absolutely yeah so uh
i like to think of decentralization
right the overly simple view of it is
it's it's a diffusion of power in a
system right and that's where i came
back to power uh for whom over whom and
of what and the whom and the water very
important there but effectively it's
taking power from a single source and
and sharing it out most simple version
uh think of a you know a kingdom when
there's literally a single king or queen
right they get power over everything a
democracy uh such as the uh you know
let's say american democracy we have
three different branches we have a bunch
of people in each of the branches right
that that's trying to take a step
towards decentralizing power away from a
single person to a larger set and then
you can argue that like truly communal
living or certain versions of anarchic
living where there is no it's kind of a
leaderless true organization where
everyone has equal power that might be
on sort of the other end of the spectrum
of sort of true everyone is on i don't
know if everyone is on the same level
but like this peer-to-peer system on the
one end and more of a truly centralized
everything comes out of one node uh on
the other end
so i wrote down does that change the
nature of the system if we have one set
of rules or one's state
that we're in or an area of state space
for some system features and one person
has all of the
tokens
and then
the system changes so that the
distribution the non-equilibrium steady
state like we might say an active
inference is at a new normal
it's at a new
stationarity or meta stationarity
it's kind of like
isn't that a different system
so
even implying that power can be spread
out
it's a it's a non-fungible asset
and it's an irreversible asset time
dependent one too
these are just like some of the as we
open the conversation i think
today but also
on a broader time scale
there are the
known unknowns and then there's the
unknown unknowns and we're going to bump
up against all of them
yeah and i really like the the i've
never used this term exactly but i
really like that you put it together the
the non-fungibility of power
because i i think that's an interesting
and important one to recognize
because
right
being aware of that especially for
people who are actively designing a
system and who are the first ones
building it you were inherently going to
have way too much power in that system
whether or not you want that power right
i think uh let's say say vitalik buterin
and ethereum is a great example right he
doesn't want to i don't right i don't
know him personally i don't want to
speak on his behalf but i have a lot of
reason to believe that he is not looking
to be the authoritarian over ethereum
right that is my genuine view of that
based on all the reading and following
of the space that i've done but vitalik
says something and everyone in the space
listens and that might have impacts on
ethereum price right so like there are
these relationships whether or not you
like it but at the same time there's
also
as a person designing these systems you
have to be willing to recognize that in
order to gain efficiency at a per at a
certain point i actually might need to
centralize the power under me but design
the system in a way so that i cannot
maintain it over time and how to
give away power
and make sure that you
don't have the ability to usurp it again
is very interesting from a system design
perspective
and even if you came into this
discussion thinking like blockchain's a
joke with three is a joke sure like
it's an open question how much
usefulness is going to come out of this
on a hundred to thousand year timeline
right i am open uh and understanding of
uh the lack of clarity of the future but
i just think the space at least daos are
worth paying attention to because i
don't see anywhere else where there's so
much open experimentation in that
direction of supposedly saying we're
here to defuse power and then watching
the actual social dynamics play and
system uh structuring around it so that
that's one of the reasons of cause of
light just go check out some doubts it's
fascinating social experiments if
nothing else
okay a few thoughts one thing is
i lived in cooperatives for many years
and so it's just so interesting to see
some of those traditions
and
failure modes
patterns
translated and then i know it's a big
theme in web 3 where the first steps
involve translating like what has
already been done okay oh you've worked
in an office before well now you're in a
virtual office
and then the future steps can be
elaborations that take it into a
different direction or use something
that couldn't have been engineered in
the physical world so
we're beginning to form the motifs and
the grammar for describing
organizational patterns design patterns
and atlases of risk for organizations
and before there was
uh
money attached to numbers it was
probably hard to do counterfactuals and
long-term tracking of money
quantitatively
and if your decision-making is
um based upon a secret handshake well
then it might be so esoteric that it has
never been investigated doesn't mean it
doesn't work it's just that now we're
implementing computational governance
hashtag medigov and implementing
programmable money and
involved in totally surveillable
communications oh just vote on this poll
well now you have the time and did
someone vote and unvote and get into so
many other pieces that weren't there in
the paper ballot and that wasn't there
until that was there
so it's a whole new set of observations
that are coming in about systems that we
had already been engaged in but then
where you get that second level
cybernetics and complexity is when we're
modifying the system with new
affordances new ways we can modify and
then that's feeding back into like
very rapid change
but by no means even maximal
yeah and so what you mentioned earlier
on uh with the first question or with
the whole idea of well once you start
decentralizing is that even the same
system at that point right once you've
changed sort of the power dynamics can
it be argued that we're looking uh
at something fundamentally different
there and i think that
part of the excite or
right there's a another area that we
need to explore and define more
terminology around in terms of that
feedback loop of
system
system architecting system running and
management and culture because right the
even if nothing else right i mean i
don't know how nothing would change in
the system going from a centralized
decentralized decision-making has to
open up like there are literal
operational things that need to go into
account
to be able to manage more people being
involved in certain decision-making
capacities
but at the same time it inherently
requires culture shift right and that's
where it comes down to that behavioral
level change for me because if it goes
from hey daniel is our benevolent
dictator in this community and no one
questions it all of a sudden both of us
are making choices and so are 50 other
people i now need to be willing and
ready to be called out for the
appropriate level of responsibility that
i hold and like hey why'd you do that
that was actually
not in line with everything else you've
said before and your views on the system
like why are you going
like now i'm accountable now i'm
responsible to my peers and i just think
that
i get worried about not enough of that
behavioral and human level coverage and
again one of the things i'm excited
about with the current experimentation
endows um right when i first got in in
2016 the amount of people uh myself
included who were like oh dallas brand
new shiny cool thing and right this is
back in 2016 when there was zero tooling
or anything for it and i right there
were people who were there much well
before then even but there was this view
of
it's a brand new thing and then all of a
sudden folks and i know like my
colleague richard brown at skirf when he
joined maker dao he was in one of these
positions where it's like y'all have
heard of co-ops before right this isn't
that like the tech might be new but the
concept isn't you've heard of a co-op
right and people would be like
and like they had never really looked
into that background and full history
and so right first there's this just
catch-up of right different domains have
relative knowledge but then once it's
these different disparate domains are
aligned and this is where i really you
you you call that the medigov community
that we're both in right i really love
the medigov community because it's not
just a web3 governance community it's a
governance community which means people
from inherently different backgrounds
with inherently different views and
and different desires of the kind of
applications they want to bring this
back to
are coming together to talk about a
topic and i think once you have those
layers of true interdisciplinary
coordinated supported action towards
trying to change a system at least
that's where i get really excited
about people coming together because i i
do just love that those kind of
different backgrounds kind of being able
to chime in on on some kind of thinking
there
a lot of places we could go as always
but
these org streams
at the academ lab it's a it's a multi
uh
street juncture there's people who might
be
familiar with or curious about active
inference but then some of these
questions
and approaches they're hearing about for
the first time and then there might be
somebody who's interested in the
governance approaches who might be
hearing about active inference for the
first time so that's kind of the fun
but
it's the microcosm of how we make
decisions and how
the differences and what our experiences
and perspectives are contribute to
something that's bigger than us
and i think that is related to your
point about uncertainty
and about changes in certainty of
different types which i think we can
take some time and think about
um
like if the plan is big enough for one
person to feel like they understand it
there's a limit to the complexity of
that plan
if you allow for stigmargy for the
ability of the plan to be understood by
one person plus their environment like
blueprints or the computer system
it's bigger than that person's one
on-board cognition so that's what a lot
of cognitive scientists call like
extended or
um
inactive cognitive processes that can
involve physical parts or modification
of the niche so that's been one trend in
neuroscience since the sort of like um
brain region a connected to brain region
b still very cool and interesting but
one of the important recent trends
is people looking into this embodied and
extended element little aside
so you have the project that that one
person can operate by themselves but
we're talking about projects that are
either
requiring multiple expertises like
almost any scientific project
or
the case where we not just could use
multiple people we might benefit from
but we're talking about governance which
is like decision making
where
it is explicitly
about creating a layer
where
multiple people are harmonizing their
view
so i think
where does uncertainty fit into that is
a fascinating area i'd love to hear more
on because uncertainty is such a core
component to active inference and the
management of uncertainty so maybe you
could give some thoughts on that and
then we can bring it back to active
yeah so i think there's a couple of
dimensions there that i don't want to
conflate either so one thing is that
right i i know
uh personality psychology i i feel like
let's just go with the big five to avoid
let's go with the one with the most
research behind it um right research uh
personality psych its own big school a
lot of differing opinions uh that's not
necessarily the focus of the current the
reason why i'm bringing it up right but
there is reason to believe there is some
biological difference between people and
again not trying to dive into all of the
nuance of that at the moment but one
element is the ease of the ability to
deal with something like uncertainty i
do not think is biologically uniform
right i think there's going to be people
who have easier time dealing with
uncertainty and people who have harder
time dealing with uncertainty and that's
just the natural disposition right then
there's the actual lived environment
that they are raised in grow up in the
culture they're in all of that which
also heavily affects that
so a question that i remember seth frey
who's uh professor seth frey who's also
in the medigov community asked during a
a podcast we had or a conference uh
panel we had organized last summer uh he
brought up this idea that he likes to
ask people of hey you when you envision
your version of utopia right imagine and
i'm butchering his exact example uh but
it was sort of oh yeah for dao it's sort
of the the the perfect out like and
envision it as a building right do you
see that building full of people or
lacking people and i think the answer to
that starts with a big dichotomy of
viewpoints around the question of
uncertainty
do you view uncertainty as an inherent
human flaw that we have to get rid of
the people and create systems that can
live in spite of humans or do you
embrace the fact that uncertainty is
just part of who we are and we will
never ever ever get rid of it fully and
we just kind of have to be okay with
letting the current wash over us and
take us where it takes us right and i am
fundamentally of the camp of like this
is all quarterly human i don't think we
can auto automate away human problems so
i i just i'm giving my own bias here i'm
very much taking this in the camp of
like well let's just dig into the
assumption that these are core human
issues and we will have to deal with the
human to human side so that that is an
important distinction i want to make
because i do think some people are
naturally predisposed or were uh or now
are predisposed due to culture and
environment to be like oh humans are the
bane of existence and uh what was the
jean-paul sartre quote um hell is other
people right like there's people who
genuinely just have a harder time for a
variety of reasons being with humans
which adds complexity to uncertainty
right so i i don't want to pretend that
everything else i'm going to say is a
blanket statement for others right i
myself am a bit of an ambivert i have
extraversion i have introversion but i i
am fundamentally human in the sense of
like i need other humans around me and i
will always prefer a messier
conversation than no conversation so
that is my bias and predisposition and
to into answering your question um so on
the actual side of uncertainty right so
existence is inherently uncertain our
parts of us want to create certainty for
a variety of reasons
right biologically we want uh certainty
so that our brain can be less freaking
out about where whether or not we're
gonna die soon right on an evolutionary
scale that's oversimplifying where like
fear responses and whatnot came from
naturally right but if you think of it
on a socio-cultural perspective
those did not naturally evolve over
millennia or over millions of years
right those were instituted and provided
for a variety of very different
perspectives right uh why we may have
been trained that a good worker is
someone who shows up to work at 9am and
leaves at 5pm or whatever the norms are
around whatever you're raised in right
there are very different uh pulls and
incentives around why that was kind of
indoctrinated into your brain aside from
oh this is just how the natural world
works right so that's also an important
gap to recognize because
why i love the lens of existential
psychology and psychotherapy is that
there's more and more
research pointing in the direction that
once
something is a core enough assumption
for someone attacking that core
assumption feels like you're attacking
them as a human being and like it feels
like it's a fundamental survival
environment for them right you might
have been in a conversation with someone
where you ask
an opinion where you just really
disagree and all of a sudden they get
into like hyper defensive mode and it's
like whoa i was just exploring an idea
why are you like i'm not trying to cut
your head off like what's happening here
and but that's how we respond when
people can question certain aspects that
are that are so based to us so
i think that again and i realize i'm
just kind of dancing around the exact
question but just uncertainty is such a
hyper complicated topic because on the
one hand it's everywhere and it's
fundamentally part of existence right
this is one thing where it's interesting
how psychedelics and buddhism and
meditation and all these other
dimensions come back to the same thing
of oh yeah life is super complicated and
i'm just never gonna get all of it and
like that's cool and you to learn how to
be okay with that right and like that's
uh on the very behavioral personal level
learning how to deal with uncertainty is
not easy for people i know i have some
folks who i absolutely adore in my life
why i tell them all the time stop being
a control freak you're making your life
harder right but that's not easy
feedback to give someone and it's kind
of useless feedback unless you actually
sit down and walk them through step by
step how to do it and what are the
things and when are you going to be
uncomfortable and when you're going to
be comfortable so part of the tricky
part of uncertainty is that it is
inherently uncomfortable
and most of us don't want to be more
uncomfortable so how do you learn how to
of knowledge of where things are going
like how do you give up control how are
you okay with knowing i have no clue
where my next step is going and yet
you're like oh no but this is awesome
and amazing and like that's actually
that is a series of contradictions
internally that is hard to consolidate
unless you have
the disposition the privilege and a few
other factors in your life to allow you
to explore it and like i recognize that
like i've spent the amount of time
digging into these things in the last 10
to 15 years because of the specific
dynamics that i was born into and other
factors that like i don't want to turn
this into a personal uh outward facing
therapy session but i'll be like i'm
happy to disclose those because i think
that
that's the dimensions of connection
right it does run that deep
okay
a lot to say there i think i'll just
sort of
retouch on a few points because they're
great and
bear reflecting upon and also because
they're some of the core
nodes
in the active inference
contextualizing and implications so
existence is uncertain you said
biologically we want certainty
relative to our generative model to
maintain persistence so this ties
together like a few key things first the
desire for
certainty arising of that desire
i added relative degenerative model
which is an active inference term like a
generative model just like in statistics
it's a reduced representation of a
complex process that spits out numbers
so it's like a generative model of the
weather and then you have one model that
takes the data and updates the
generative model and then you have a
generative model that can create
expected data and then compare incoming
results so that's a key part of the
predictive brain bayesian brain
active inference and then to maintain
persistence
is where it ties in with
identity and with thermodynamic survival
so that's kind of on also on that more
technical side that's what ties us to
like non-equilibrium thermodynamics
now
for cultural entities
oh if we were only a thermobacterium
that uncertainty is tied up with
other people
so
yes we also are dealing with uncertainty
about other things too and different
people in different situations different
phenomena they deal with
but across the board
it's pretty much other people and so
that brings up some active themes like
having a shared generative model
reflected by a shared narrative
so like we don't all have to agree what
role in the movie we are but
if it's different genre
that doesn't even mean it's bad it just
means that some people might get
surprised if that's what they expect
and then some other active things we
talk about are like ostensive cues
which are used to signal
attention and then the way that we talk
about
how and where attention is directed
that's the regime of attention and so
when the music stops after the middle of
the orchestra but everybody knows that's
not the time to clap
what does that say about the culture
and about what everyone's attention is
and that's how they signal that they're
all part of the same listening
community for example when they do or
don't take the action of clapping so
social entities again whether it's just
social projects like exchanging value
for shoes
or whether we're talking about the
social media which is the governance and
decision making implicitly and
explicitly that's where
it's such a great topic eugene and
you've brought because
it is about that individual micro level
decision making and regime of attention
i'm scanning a proposal in my web 3 you
know dashboard but my
literal pupil gazing
and my blood sugar is going to be
mattering
and so how can we really think
holistically about the regime of
attention
and the cues and the affordances
and all of that
for
humans who we're designing for we don't
want to be in the matrix pods
we want them to have a thriving life
which is going to be different for
different people and so it's just such a
great nexus that you've brought together
so any thoughts and then a few more
active points
oh yeah i know i love that because that
directly also ties into and i love the
way you articulated that so thank you
for running through that and i also uh
an element that i that i've been
thinking about in the last couple of
days that feeds nicely into that uh in
terms of right how do our how do our
models get updated in terms of uh some
of these social dynamics and the
importance of exposure as a step to
better managing uncertainty right i know
as someone who like i'm not a a uh coder
that was not what my parents showed me
the the process that i went down as a
kid i was not the kind to just figure it
out on my own so i still have this weird
fear of technology like the first time i
need to go do something deeply technical
i'm like i'm just gonna break everything
it's like it's illogical i know it's
illogical i've done enough to know that
it does not make sense and each time i
do it it feels a little better and sort
of my internal models get updated by all
the uh you know
by deciding to
direct my attention and understanding
the fact that because this is something
my existing models don't know how to
accurately predict i'm going to
experience a certain amount of
discomfort there and
taking the meta-level attention to
realize that that's happening is already
a great step to being able to work
through more and more of that kind of
uncertainty and discomfort because for
me it's whatever the tools are for
individuals that are important to like
hey are you noticing you're
uncomfortable now great next time try to
like catch it a little earlier and a
little earlier and a little earlier and
eventually you'll hopefully start
gaining enough of a sense of what series
of actions or thoughts leads to an
unpleasant state and then being able to
modulate certain elements of that right
so again there's also the other
dimension of this a privilege right i've
kind of alluded to it a few times but i
also
never want to be critical about these
things because we're all coming from
vastly different areas of our lives and
i know in times in my life where i was
you know living paycheck to paycheck and
barely making ends meet it's not
possible to focus on these higher order
things like i i was i was very much
struggling with that at those points in
time now that i have a little more
luxury and comfort i'm able to you know
spend my free time pondering in a
different way which i think is also very
important to recognize
when some of us think about you know
financial distribution and paying it
forward and sharing in abundance and all
those kind of
or effective altruism or all these other
things
at the end of the day we all have so
many options to just inject a little bit
of positivity for someone else and the
more that we choose to do that the more
we can potentially free them up to have
a little more room in their cycle in a
day to day to put their attention
somewhere where it might not have been
going before and of course it's
it's utopic to think of like oh i see
someone struggling i do a nice thing for
them great they ponder the philosophy of
life as a right like that's a lovely
ideal that probably happens almost never
but like more realistically right if we
as a because we are inherently social
because coordination is so at the core
of what we do
and because there's a lot of systems and
other pressures around us telling us who
we supposedly are right and us trying
that having a navigate of well
supposedly i'm selfish or i'm collective
right depending on which part of the
world you're coming from that could be a
core narrative you hear or all these
other dimensions and
all of this
just comes back to
in my mind like uncertainty equals
complexity and control in different
areas right because
life is wild like i don't even pretend
to be able for my brain to be able to
grasp the level of complexity and to be
able to put it into words because it's
just beyond what i am capable of
comprehending but
i'm okay with that and the being okay
with that and the desire of control of
complexity is a much more
dangerous thing and directly related to
that it might seem like a tangent but is
the idea of like fomo or fear of missing
out right it's this control desire of
wanting to like oh i know these things
and i have to be able to control my
schedule so i can get all these supposed
desires out of it right and the whole
idea of knowing yourself and how to
really know yourself is a whole separate
thread i'm not going to go down the
moment but i recently heard the term
jomo and not just to give more whatever
terms but like the whole idea of joy of
missing out right to know that hey if
i'm choosing to be here with you right
now doing this sure in the back of my
mind i can cycle through all the things
i chose not to do as a result of this
and i'm missing out on in this window or
i could just be like no i'm super
freaking lucky that you asked me to be
here with you and we now get to share
this experience and whoever hears it
gets to hear it and boom i've focused
all my attention i don't have to worry
about adding all those other things
which in turn right the whole idea of
fear of missing out and being always
worried and wanting to like control
these other factors where it just leads
to this place where you are stealing
your own attention from yourself away
from the things that on your deathbed
you might be realized were the most
important to you and this is also to
take another sidestep why in my opinion
meditating on death is very important
because that's one of the few things
that can help you realize of like oh
this was literally the last second how
do i feel about everything that got here
like that's one of the only ways in my
opinion you can like deeply understand
how truly satisfied are you with the
suite of activities you choose to fill
your time because a lot of us have we
are shackled by things we have to deal
with and that is a different set of
thinking and emotional judgment that
should go to that direction if you are
hyper privileged and not happy with how
you're spending your time you deserve a
very different conversation than someone
who you know is barely making ends meet
putting food on the table for a family
of three or whatever right like we also
have to be realistic with ourselves and
know how harsh we should or should not
be with ourselves so i'm happy to go
into more like some of my own personal
psychological tools on that side but i
don't want to just keep rambling
well this is already quite a unique and
different um
discussion on active it's really
interesting so few thoughts
uncertainty is the core of
decentralization that's what you had
brought up earlier and then you
connected that to treating each other
nicely
so it's up to us on the edge to act
infer and serve
the way that we expect and prefer it
signals to ourselves not the least of
all what kind of person we are like are
you the kind of person where when the
nft is worth a hundred
you give five away and
or
are you stressed about 130 because it
could be higher because it's a number so
it's like
if we are going to have that different
system with decentralization
it will be not just like
um part of the picture that people are
nice to each other on the edges that
will be the system so either we're not
in that world or we are
and so expecting that somebody else is
going to
redistribute our centralized taxes to do
that is at the very least emboldening
that system
and then also it signals to others what
kind of people they are
expecting to see if you pull 10
red and one blue out of an urn
bayesian statistics works a certain way
to update priors it could be very tight
precision or very loose precision but
at some point you're going to be like
are there more of this one kind than the
other kind and so that's related to
statistics but also the way that our
brain the bayesian brain predictive
brain
uses things like statistics
and that includes our
cognitive
biases as they say but of course tobias
is to take signal out of the world so
what will those signals be and then also
when we
um
provide people with material support
you're bringing it back to like it again
it's not just a solipsistic
single trajectory optimizing strategy
there's like a level of strategy where
it's not like the individual must lose
because the group has benefited it's
like
it's an ensemble
and one's agency and their perception
and action their perry personal space
has a certain spatial and temporal scale
and if one doesn't care about leaving
the future a wasteland
then
we can talk about that in this model
with their expectations and preferences
maybe they have
other reasons to think that way but
there's a lot there too
yeah you know i mean just to start at
the end there i mean the thing that that
i think about a lot in that sense is i
wish
that and i'm just taking four because i
believe forbes or bloomberg whoever does
the billionaires list right i i wish
instead of doing the list of here's the
people with the most wealth in their
bank encounter that they can just claim
their name is directly affiliated with
that we tracked
who's created the most jobs in the last
year who's actually distributed the most
wealth on the planet like how many
people get to put food on the table that
they didn't afford if it wasn't for
someone else or some kind of other
metrics that can be deemed socially
impressive
that actually reside on the the social
dimension and not just thinking of us as
individuals because the whole yeah i
mean we can i don't want to take us more
off the pathway with uh just like the
you know history and wealth and what not
in in the states and any questions
around that but for me it does
i don't know one piece of research that
i really appreciate in this direction is
the uh oh i'm forgetting all of their
names but the the the the group in in
siberia far out in russia that starting
in the 70s if not the 80s did the the
training of the arctic foxes to see how
quickly right and arctic foxes are
notoriously not friendly or pleasant uh
how quickly can they get them to be
fully domesticated and i believe it was
within 10 generations if i'm remembering
correctly but roughly at the time this
is still when i mean especially in the
soviet union where science was
complicated for a variety of reasons
especially anything that had social
implications to it and not just pure
math or physics um
but no there was not many there were not
many people at the time who truly
thought yes you could domesticate a wild
animal shortly because there was still
much more of the you know on the human
level of uh
of we're just rigid creatures we are the
way we are we don't change so all of a
sudden that we saw that hey you know you
can actually very select very clearly
select for certain features that get us
there right the interesting question for
me becomes what were the features right
what's the thing that you pick
generation to generation for selective
mating that actually led to a much more
domesticated version of the fox not that
domestication is an end goal but it is
one of a few strands of research that is
trying to explore on our evolutionary
scale what were the actual features that
led to us being such good coordinating
creatures you know up until society and
modern civilization kicked in because
then things got much more complicated um
but there's very good reason to believe
that it's niceness it's kindness right
and like think about a social dynamic
sure there might be the super strong
macho whatever you know
you know not even trying to gender it
right there could be the pure by
traditional like there's the the person
that can squash everyone else in the
system right and they think of like oh
we all have to defer to that person but
that seems itself to be a social
construct right if you actually look at
what what decent amounts of scientific
literature starting to point to that it
is nice and niceness and that the more
we can try to create a system where that
is what is rewarded and encouraged am i
pretending that everyone is going to
become nice no there's always going to
be like there's always going to
be people who don't want to play well
i'm just not going to let that stop me
from being nice to other people right
you can either have someone be mean to
you and be like well why should i bother
being nice if they're not going to be
nice to me or i can be like yeah people
are people right some are just going to
suck and that's just how it goes because
when you have this much uncertainty
there's no way you can like all of
what's in that uncertainty right if you
can find certain strands of it just be
okay with the complexity of it and find
comfort in knowing that i will never
solve this riddle but i get to be part
of just playing around and tinkering
with it like that alone can be really
empowering and exciting so i don't know
for me i i keep trying to reframe
niceness as not just like a
a
either a you know a thing that your
parents taught you to do because that's
just the thing that they want you to do
whereas this you know it's thing it's
actually socially weak and it's
i don't know i don't buy in any of that
and i as someone who
enjoys it i i now enjoy genuinely just
being nice to people or when people are
nice to me it's nice to see that there
is research coming out to say hey hey
there's reasons on a neural level why
that feels good but also be on a longer
evolutionary scale why that is the
feature set that we should focus on in
system design to actually get us
collaborating better together
but that doesn't solve the fact that
there's a lot of incentives around not
pushing us towards niceness and for me
that means if we're trying to create
systems where that is a thing we want to
optimize towards but that is in a larger
structure where that is not a key
priority right that just means we're
gonna have a tremendous amount of
dissonance between those two systems and
if you're trying to fight that good
fight you know good just in the sense of
being kind to each other um
it's gonna suck right there's no there's
no way it cannot unless all of these
systems break down and we build a new
and to me that's a much scarier option
is anything that involves like truly
bringing down mass global systems i
don't see how that happens without very
intense international affairs that i
would personally be okay without seating
so i i think that you just have to be
unless you truly want world war iii and
you know near extinction and then we
rebuild from there i think the only
alternative is we just got to suffer
through the fact that there's it's going
to take us a while but we'll get there
eventually but just be good to people
and a lot of amazing things can happen
from that
wgmi well thanks for bringing that
important perspective sometimes
it's easy to get caught up in how many
papers are written on active inference
and just the rhythm and the micro
and
that's exactly what you're really
calling towards so let me
bring it back towards some active
core terms and like ideas and let's see
where maybe the niceness and some of
those ideas come back into play so
um we already talked about uncertainty
being one of the key
factors and that not being like a hot
take or contrarian opinion it's like a
de facto understanding that what is
happening from a sensory perspective is
not mere signal processing
and filtering and the way that a one
directional neural network processes
sense but actually like an active
generative process that's compared to
incoming
scarce data that's why we like don't
have a blind spot in our eyes and things
like that so
that is not contentious it is a core
piece of active inference however
now in active inference
there's action amidst uncertainty
and so that's a lot like the action
perception loop or the ooda loop for
those who are familiar with it
and
every single cycle every crank that's
run
inference and action are co-occurring
and so there's
a few angles that first is that we never
make a system
where we're expecting to do something
that it's not enabled to do or vice
versa so even just qualitatively before
the computers come out this helps think
about how subunits are connected like if
the forager ant is waiting for the
interaction from the nurse ant but the
nurse ant doesn't have that affordance
there's a missing piece in the system's
design and so yes it is going to be a
whole other level of emergence with
fine-tuning that interaction but just at
the level of thinking about what the
entities and their connections are and
how they influence the niche
active reminds us that action and
perception are integrated at that level
also not unique to active inference very
similar to any kind of cybernetic or
agent-based modeling framework
but what is different is the way that we
can talk about
different types of uncertainty
and even things like multi-scale
uncertainty or for example uncertainty
about events and there's other talks i
hope people go down the rabbit hole 101
ways because we've talked a lot about
different uncertainty
formalisms on active lab and i hope
there's a lot more develop on those
areas but just to say that
again one could imagine like using that
earlier example of being in a movie in a
genre you could have high precision on
the genre but then maximum uncertainty
about what is going to occur next in
that like a thriller with a
stereotypical enculture set of music and
lights and all of that
or you could know exactly what was
happening oh it's just counting down the
numbers one after another with high
precision but not understand the
narrative component
so i think to connect it to
web whatever in systems design
what is it that we want to reduce our
uncertainty on
and how can we
really bring our attention to the types
of uncertainty
that matter for humans affect for how we
feel in our phenomenology and like the
system uncertainty notes like if the
block arrival time starts getting too
wild
we don't want that to go off the rail
that's like a technical use of
uncertainty minimization and control
but then this
embodied perspective on humans as active
agents
brings the human level of uncertainty in
and
not everybody wants to be on a live
stream
not everybody even wants to
have a say on a decision-making proposal
but
how could we reduce their uncertainty
about what they do
expect and prefer
and customize that and i think that's
where
cognitive frameworks like active could
come into play
yeah
i mean that's one where i guess it's
also important to note that i don't know
if the quote-unquote average person in
web 3 and i have no clue what that even
means but if if if you pulled you know
there's going to be east denver next
month i would actually this would be a
fun fun study to run if i had the time
and energy but you asked 10-ish thousand
people or whatever certain amount of
people are flocking to denver for this
conference uh
what what term is at the core of web
three and i actually wonder how many of
them would put uncertainty and how many
people would tell me i'm a madman for
thinking that that that's a core of
decentralization because i think that a
lot of what i hear at least is the idea
of oh we're adding an automated trust
layer right so that's actually
minimizing uncertainty what are you
talking about we're adding uncertainty
we're trying to uh you don't have to
trust in people you can trust in systems
you know you don't have to trust in a
banker at someone at j.p morgan you can
trust the protocol instead and you know
it's all great um
but i mean i think that right that goes
back to some of the other aspects we
were talking about well on what level
and what part of the system because if
you're actually talking on technical
architecture uh yes you could just have
less humans needing to interact at a
certain point but if then you're talking
the complete set of full human
interactions using that protocol it
right this a few years ago there was the
debate on what's more relevant for
blockchains off-chain governance or
on-chain governance you know like can
you auto automate things that it's a
quick yeah or an and it's all
automatable and it's all interacted uh
purely through code or do you need
humans talking to each other
and i feel like there are some you know
like interest rate going up or down yeah
sure those things might be on chain
governance oriented anything that
actually involves more complex questions
or even more complicated right with the
distinction being that complicated is
still modelable complex has emergent
behavior um right even with complicated
things that could already kind of get
get challenging uh in terms of just
getting humans to agree on things so um
i i am not a big proponent of uh
the goal of all of this being humans
have to decide less i think that yes
it's always great to you know do we
right there's a few aspects here which
i'm myself uncertain about right there's
an in there's almost a unstoppable force
that is more technology advancements of
technology automation to a certain
degree is happening to the world to us
whether or not we like it um the
question is what are we trying to
automate and i feel like that's still
very much an open question and i i am
i don't know i
the hmm let me see the best way to move
this forward i think
at its core i've heard one thing the
idea of its coordination all the way
down right in the crypto space or web 3
space whatever that at the end of the
day what is the most base thing that
huma that as a species we are doing we
are coordinating right because if we're
already taking forgiven that we exist uh
we there's many of us here and we have
desires then we have to ask of like oh
well how did we get here right it seems
that coordination was a very key part of
differentiating us uh from some of our
other ancestors down the line and so
for me coordinating is inherently
uncertain right just people being people
together is an inherently uncertain task
because unless you heavily constrain and
force people to be less themselves right
if you're telling someone don't be
yourself be this thing i want you to be
then then you're minimizing uncertainty
right you're telling like i don't want
daniel i want a version of daniel that i
would like to see right that is
minimizing uncertainty but
right the whole idea of seeing people
for who they are and where they're at
right that that's adding complexity
that's adding uncertainty that's saying
i don't need to know where you're at i
just need to recognize the fact that i
will never know where you're at because
i'm a different human i have a different
lived experience than you all i can do
is with my limited abilities try to
project and understand what's going on
with you and use a mix of empathy right
can i just feel those emotions and
compassion can i rationalize that
feeling and do something about it and
for me compassion is much more important
than empathy because
empathy is deep and
psychologically taxing and very limiting
in terms of the amount of people we can
direct it towards compassion and i just
finished uh rutger bregman's uh
humankind book right where he and it's
not as though it's his idea but the
whole idea of rational compassion being
much more of a scalable concept than
pure empathy because if you try to
empathize with all people on the planet
that's just not going to work in any way
possible right rational empathy can be
something that we utilize as a more
focused rational compassion excuse me it
can be more of a tool in our tool belt
to
not just fall into tribal camps but to
try to actually think of how can i see
your pain as a person who is totally
different than me in every way shape or
form has our pain and that kind of
reframing is a very very powerful thing
but i also want to i want to jump back
to what you started with because i i
know it's a active uh it's it's a given
in certain circles but i for me that's
actually part of the problem is where
you were talking about you know the
whole idea that like we don't know our
realities or brains or projections or uh
prediction machines all these um
you know like you mentioned the blind
spot like i don't know do most people
realize that we literally have a blind
spot in our vision and the only reason
we still think we always see things is
because our brains predict over it
effectively and
i wonder if you came up to a person on
the street when you're like hey look
around that's not objective reality
would they tell you that you're on drugs
and crazy or would they be like yes yes
let's have a scientific dialogue right
and i excuse me for the the previous
statement but like it's the point being
there right that people don't react
kindly at least i've had that reaction a
lot of the time even with well-educated
people so it's not a pure education
perspective and for me
getting people like that comes back to
people embracing uncertainty right how
do we encourage people to recognize that
i fundamentally don't know anything
about anything
hopefully through education and a lot of
intention about my attention i will try
to learn a few things but in the grand
scheme of collective knowledge i will
never know anything
and like that's a weird thing to admit
to myself like as much as i really try
hard i can hopefully learn some concepts
and frameworks that broadly apply to
whatever environments i find myself in
but in the grand scheme of information
even if you have photographic memory you
practically know nothing just because
there's so so much of it and i don't
know for me that's also been more of a
liberating thought whereas when i was
younger it was always a very fear-based
like oh no that just means work harder
whereas now it's like no just embrace
the uncertainty embrace the washing over
of i will never do everything so just be
intentional about your attention and
what you do want to do and make the most
out of that so i feel like i went on a
hard tangent on that one but that just
felt important to call out oh do i have
some some points directly to this so
thank you for sharing it so
um
yes there are niches on the internet
or in real life where
it is um
a beginning point that the brain is a
predictive entity or at least could be
modeled like that which we
discuss is the difference between
instrumentalism are we just applying
statistical models and we're just making
no claims to the territory we're just
talking about maps we're like
cartographers
or
are we making ontological statements
like the brain does active inference
realism instrumentalism is like i find
it useful to study the brain using this
model so if someone used a linear
regression they wouldn't say the brain
was a linear regressor we're doing that
with instrumentalism for active
also there's realism so that's like the
one point to make but you pointed like
how some people resist
that um
sense of re-aligning
their generative model to this idea that
we are
experiencing our generative model so i
think there's a few pieces
the meta is um we've all been wrong
before
we've been convinced on something and
been wrong so your emotional conscious
experience which is only the tiniest
fraction of the iceberg
just simply can be
incorrect
by virtue of the way you've had
interactions in the past
um so it doesn't need to be framed as
right or wrong
there are some useful
components to thinking about the brains
of predictive machine and it gives us
unique predictions and explanations so
for people who enjoy those features this
is a useful way to think about the brain
so one example is like vision where the
anatomy of the eye
is clear that there's a blind spot
that's off on the side and also there's
different resolution and color
perception across the eye so we're
perceiving with our mind not our eye but
of course input to the retina and light
activation matters it just turns out
that there's a lot more of an actively
updating process and it turns out that's
the one that we're perceiving without
the blind spot rather than the incoming
sensory data and that also applies to
our other sensory features
what's cool
and closes the loop between individual
decision making and behavior and like
science as a human endeavor
is that it turns out that in order to
get good information about that
generative model one has to do informed
sampling like our eyes are circading
around we don't perceive that so that's
another example of why we're perceiving
the stable version of vision which is
not being received by any sensor
and it
circades around the vision
to reduce uncertainty goes where there
is visual uncertainty and so that
generative model isn't just like a sort
of one frame per second of what is
predicted to be there it also carries
like extra information like where are
you uncertain in your visual field
so that is like the process of being a
scientist where you're getting
experimental observations but then
there's a system you didn't observe
sometimes you destroy the cell to
measure it or you have to kill the
animal or whatever it is
but there's
observations and then there's the hidden
system state and it turns out that that
maps onto a lot of statistical models
like the partially observable markov
decision processes which integrate that
separation between observation and
hidden state inference
in the context of action
selection so that's kind of the family
that active inference is in and then
just the second
point was about the
empathy
and
complex online systems
and another active inference term is
this thinking through other minds so
it's related to theory of mind just like
it sounds
and it's referring to when one's uh
counterfactuals or their cognition is
based upon
how they expect something will be
evaluated by others
like
i will do x with my clothing or speech
this is it could be implicit or an
explicit
uh self-talk
because others will see me this way
because my partner will see me this way
or because my dao will see me this way
so that helps us
get a handle on complex social cognition
if we can have
models of cognitive entities that can
engage in reflection and have anxiety
and then um that's where roles
in complex systems might come into play
so you said that roles reduce
uncertainty
i agree
sometimes they reduce uncertainty about
one node but then they expand it like
you're gonna be
the saxophone soloist
and i'm looking forward to how you
improvise
then
so it's like
we reduce the group's uncertainty who's
gonna be the soloist but then that's
what opens up the certainty um
distribution in another way or like
we're playing chess when you can have
brilliant games of chess
because there's constraint and there's
like roles and but if if people were
always mutating the games of chess
there wouldn't be as many classic games
because like the structure would just be
a lot more superficial and so roles
might be able to help us reduce
uncertainty about certain features
and then humanize because oh they're a
learner in this meeting
amazing
citizen science is so great i love
working with people who are just
learning about research
and then everyone can feel included in
that even if it takes them 15 years
to learn linear algebra
in that one meeting
it could be very
okay and nobody would be getting graded
for example
yeah
and i think that especially the last uh
element that you were talking about
there i think it's important to stress
the difference between
embracing uncertainty and maximizing for
uncertainty because i feel as though
people might unintentionally hear the
idea of embracing uncertainty as as that
is an implication that more uncertainty
is always a good thing um
where i actually think when you're
designing a system if you want people to
flourish giving them too much
uncertainty is a debilitating factor so
right there's the there's the system
design component from the actual
function of the system and then there's
the cultural psychological component
around it and
right on the cultural psychological
component that's where as a designer of
a system or community or company or
whatever
you think of how you set that cultural
tone and you set right you by
interacting with people in in various
ways that you do in your organization
you set a certain tone of are you
embracing uncertainty or do you always
want to especially if you're the leader
in your organization do you need to show
this facade of like no i'm always
certain on everything right because that
actually sets a cultural tone of it's
okay to be fakely certain right like
there's no way you're certain about
everything i think every leader is
inherently uncertain about things
because just of how many options there
are
but you also need to know when to be
okay with that uncertainty and in spite
of it to still be like no we're doing
this one thing and that's the direction
we're headed it right like that's its
own
its own interesting aspect but i i think
that
when it comes to designing any system
whether it's web3 crypto whatever you're
you know you're carving out an
internship for someone like whatever it
is but
creating constraints
and a sandbox is very important for
people's comfort level so i think the
way i like to think of it is the amount
of constraints need to be greater
while people are newer to things and the
more they're exposed to it potentially
the more you can open up for them right
again not everyone is going to be not
everyone thrives in having uncertainty
some people need their hand held through
it and then they can start thriving some
people at least i i don't have enough
evidence over a long enough time period
to know but there are some people for
whom adding uncertainty just everything
collapses and crumbles around them and
like their role in the system just
cannot proceed and like if you're
building right you can think of dowse as
these fantastic new futuristic
these are employment opportunities for
people right like people need to buy
food and they get it now from
decentralized decentralized ecosystems
in some capacity so right you can't this
is where i actually i still am unclear
on how i think because if you go to a
lot of these communities and you're like
oh how do i get started just do stuff
and that's great for the privilege right
what happens when someone's like well i
hate my job i think i can help you here
i want to help out but i need you to
like help me help you out because how
else am i going to pay for my kids food
tomorrow and i can't make a change in my
ecosystem and i can't just spend right i
don't know how many hours your your
listeners have spent trying to get
onboarded into various dows it can be a
painful experience right a lot of these
groups were started by a bunch of
brilliant people who come together and
it's other brilliant people who get
pulled in and then all of a sudden when
it's well what's the ramp way for
someone who has no clue what the heck is
going on here that was an afterthought
and that was kind of produced after the
fact when someone complained about it or
once we had enough time and so
yeah uncertainty is this fascinating
concept because you have to know
when adding more of it is a good thing
versus when adding it is a bad thing
and you have to know from a system
design perspective
where do you culturally embrace it
versus where do you actively try to get
rid of it at all costs because that's
what's going to help your team thrive
and you can still embrace it and want to
get rid of it in certain areas like
those are not inherently contradictory
right you could be like i don't know
what the next year holds from the market
but in this specific function of
operations where i'm going to hyper
control this in every possible way so
that i know that outcome with high
probability right think of anyone in a
supply chain if they tell you where they
know what's happening with the resources
three years from now they're lying no
one knows what's happening three years
from now right but they could model it
better than someone else right but in
their actual supply chain they could
control that fabricated room so that
they literally know every speck of dust
in the air right and that that might be
worth mitigating uncertainty there while
still embracing it in the longer context
okay few points first in active
inference where we put action on an
important grounding with other kinds of
inference processes
it's not just uncertainty about the
outside world which of course it's easy
to spiral on it's actually also
uncertainty about our action so huddle
i have high precision on my action
policy with respect to btc
no matter what
color on that site that day
so that helps uncouple and put space
between or it's staked it's locked or
it's a multi-sig so that can offload
individual level uncertainty and anxiety
onto programmatic systems so then
the certainty in systems design so i
don't remember who initially told me
this anecdote but like
the people who we today call politicians
will say things like we're not going to
sleep until this happens and we're gonna
it will happen
but no one says it's so important the
bridge be designed properly that we're
not gonna sleep and
it's a serious issue yes lives are on
the line we're building a bridge
so how do we do it
we have bridge management and design and
processes around making sure that it
actually works so as governance
becomes less about the virtue signal of
we're not going to sleep until we figure
this out and more about
we're actually doing systems engineering
we can treat it more like the bridge and
say yeah oh yeah we're all here we
direct a regime because we care about
the people on the bridge
and that's why we're doing it this way
and so that will be a huge difference
than just who can signal loudest and
then just one other
point was like research to bring this
back to decentralized science and
research is a multi-year task like
i've been doing
entomology insect biology and insect
genetics for 10 years
and i'm only beginning in this area
so
it's cool to be excited about many areas
that's why there's always been like
complexity and it's awesome to be
open-ended and love exploring those
areas but for research and application
like the cutting edge it is a multi-year
upskilling reskilling process
if you're not on the cutting edge and on
the cutting edge it's just continually
that plus sometimes even more
so being okay
with all of that
and then just
recognizing that it's a multi-year
process and whatever mechanisms for
whomever and when and however
we need something that's going to not
just rapid assemble the bounty team and
then do the multi-sig and then leave
some people might find those
opportunities appealing
but we need to recognize that a huge
amount of this is going to be like
multi-year
communities and the kinds of
relationships and small teams that will
only scale if we're all engaged in it
yeah yeah that makes me particularly
think about two aspects kind of
community size and temporality of change
or the time dimensions of change and on
the on the community size front
and again right this is i this is not an
area where i think anyone has the answer
right this is just me me kind of uh
giving my own views and personal biases
here but i i strongly believe in
especially just exploring what i've been
exploring in this world and generally um
trying to learn in the direction that
i've been trying to learn
what i get excited about dows is
actually providing the digital
infrastructure
for a super nuanced
global landscape of communities of
communities where
at the end when it's humans actually
organizing and making decisions together
actively or at least most on kind of the
consumer end so to say that those are
going to be in in tiny pockets and above
those pockets will be bigger and bigger
communities and points of connection
that are more global and bring them all
together right the whole idea of say for
something like a supply chain how can
you have a system that you have the
global benefits right
for consumers
it would be great if amazon covered all
of the global distribution right for the
people working in those factories it
would not be great for that and possibly
for our planet i don't know on their
global footprint well enough but right
there is this idea of how can we get to
a point where we have global efficiency
around a variety of topics while still
having very localized interaction and
nuance and
this for me on a very abstract level is
why decentralization is important
because we are currently barreling
towards a world of more and more
centralization right it's the monopolies
because or whatever i don't want to have
pointed terms but you know companies
tend to have more market share they try
like their only goal is how do we not
just grow the pie but how do we make the
biggest share of the pie hours right
there's a lot of fundamental incentives
that
that are not the healthiest so to say
but at the same time having global
efficiency around certain functions such
as a supply chain such as global money
such as global identity would be great
but having those certain infrastructures
available on the global scale is very
different than what you would actually
the environments you would organize in
as an individual and i i don't want to
be part of 50 million person communities
because then i'm going to be overwhelmed
and i'm going to have no clue how to
navigate it and i have no clue what the
heck to do in that i'm just going to
find my core group of people of i don't
know a few a handful to a few hundred
and somewhere in there and that's
probably going to be more those size
communities that i play in so bringing
it back to more dows and especially dow
research dows right now uh so i can also
share with you the link i don't remember
if i did ahead of time but i'm just
putting together a different
organizations that are in one way or
another playing around with uh the
intersection of dows and science in some
kind of capacity and some of these
groups have nothing to do with web3
except that they're using it as a dow as
a mechanism of coordinating and funding
right the actual science is all
non-related to web three um and that
gets me super excited and i think uh
thinking from the course tiniest aspects
of like us as a group of scientists
where do we want our research or
whatever we're doing to have an impact
great right and then for people like me
who
for whatever weird reason love building
infrastructure or just like open source
and just like operational layers right
like how do i work with those separate
pockets to be like hey you all shouldn't
be worried about the operations there
should be a lay a dow of operations
wrapped around all of the signs
that help you do the operations and
there should be a fundraising now
wrapped around all the signs now that
can connect to all the main science
funders across the planet and right
there are these mechanisms that just
incentives have never existed there
before
and i honestly don't think they're there
yet these are still from my vantage
point these are still public goods that
in any other context but web3 would
comfortably say yeah we need tax or
charity to make this run but web 3 being
web 3 those are both bad words right so
we have to pretend that it's oh well
we'll just keep having money trickle in
because right now money grows on trees
and no one's working about worried about
sustainable funding 50 years from now
right but at some point uh this fun part
of our dance comes to an end and we have
you know
we're not just growing on on the huddle
beliefs at some point at some point we
recognize like no we've reached probably
the zenith right and at that point how
are we actually going to fund anything
that's an infrastructure layer and right
now there's some really interesting
experimentation i know even metagov the
community we've mentioned they have a
doubt a fun research in the direction of
governance like i love these kind of
experiments but again peer review and
that's one that we want to take a
serious focus at at smart contract
research forum because we don't see
who's playing in that direction we see
some people playing on the publishing
side we see people wanting to do the
research side but right but the core
infrastructure is just it's less sexy
it's not as fun to build and you don't
get to have your name out on things
right so like that that's where it's
like i i that's where we want to take a
focus on what we want to add but i want
to be respectful of time because i know
we're getting dangerously close to the
end here
let's have some last thoughts and then
we should we can do a dot two we can do
more so um
yes bolts business operational legal
technical social
that's one acronym that we use those are
all important for research
and if the person who has the most
knowledge of equations is doing the
accounting
it
is not efficient allocation and then
font like formal documents ontology
narrative and tools so those are some of
the frameworks
first thinking about systems design and
then review
um well here on the live stream where
we've done like 36 paper discussions
over the last two years or so
um
we often wonder about where that could
go so um
having 10 people look through it and
different people do different thing one
person runs the code one really digs in
the citations
it's a live stream
people are
rewarded by participating in the lab
we're learning by doing i'm spending
more time reading active inference
papers than writing them by far and most
researchers probably are too otherwise
one starts getting disconnected from the
pack so how can we make that
contribution those notes
that people make in review
not like accept or reject
but yes and
and then we have other people's
perspective on something it doesn't mean
that it's right so there's so many
things that can be done with knowledge
annotation and
that sounds like a great area to look
into i totally agree that there's been a
lot of focus on financialization
tokenization
um conceptualization
in research and the parts that
i
would like to hear more from
is that recognition of the multi-year
challenge
and about what kind of research people
want to specifically do and spearhead
and hold on
tight through because even when you're
getting paid as a grad student in a
really lucky situation
it can still be challenging so when
those features like health care and
weekly check-ins with a mentor aren't in
place
that's the situation where
research will be happening
so um
[Music]
what are your last thoughts or where do
you think we should go from here
yeah i mean i think right careful
experimentation i think is very
important right now and i also uh i
think it's important for the folks who
are experimenting to be aware of the
potentiality of their experiments and i
think we've all seen the how
move fast and break things without any
concern for potentialities of outcomes
can lead to very bad outcomes so you
know for folks who are experimenting
with something that realistically is
almost has a you know a sub 1
probability of ever having a meaningful
negative impact on a person yeah go
crazy have as much fun as you can
experimenting in that direction right
the more it's actually closer to where
people are making their livelihood and
are spending their lives and that it can
negatively affect a lot of people the
more that review focus and the more
questioning there needs to be about how
do we make sure that we're doing this
right so
honestly i'm just really excited we're
still early in 22. uh it's been a
whirlwind these last few years in so
many different ways you know i'm just
hoping that there's more chances for
collect uh coordination for
collaboration and especially for folks
in the in the web 3 space
i don't mean to make whatever
predictions at some point the market is
going to turn right i'm hoping we
haven't started yet maybe we're already
at the beginning of the bear market who
knows i'm not an i'm not going to
pretend to not financial advice not
scientific advice not legal
no
no no formal advice
human to human personal advice maybe
nothing beyond that right but
i'm very interested to see once we hit
the bear market what does the
collaboration look like because i think
that's actually going to be where a lot
of gold comes uh and a lot of just
intellectual brilliance comes out
because then a lot of the noise is going
to run away so i know a lot of people
because their bank accounts are
horrified of when the market turns and i
get it but i actually think it's going
to be very good and healthy for the
industry over the next three to five
years
and the way you
raise so many important issues
big thanks for that and with the review
it's almost like we are focusing on the
publication and the research and the
funding sides but that piece of review
it's almost like the first one we need
that is a strange loop of science and we
need review
on the plans for desai and review on the
frameworks for building the plans for
desai and on all of that and so that's
like review guild
is really
a strong place for people who want to
learn by doing and be a big leverage
point it's like the coefficient of the
grants and the way that knowledge by
people who are off doing field work gets
incorporated is through
review especially in these new
structures which we probably haven't
even seen yet but they're not going to
look like proceedings of the uk 1600
alchemists it's going to be quite
different
that is for sure yeah and for anyone if
you are interested in in peer review or
these kind of decentralized science
centralized peer reviewed decentralized
publication of research please let me
know always feel free to reach out and i
love connecting with folks and talking
to a lot of folks who are trying to
solve this problem from different
perspectives and trying to figure out
how we all come together to at least
share our learnings if nothing else and
i'll definitely make sure to coordinate
with you in the active community on that
side let's do a dot two with a panel
in a in one or a few months let's check
back in on some of these themes revisit
the slides hear from some new
perspectives update on the projects that
we talked about today and just see where
we're at
sounds like a plan thanks for having me
again daniel
thank you eugene awesome conversation
much appreciated bye
you